

Curriculum Vitae

Mohammad Rizwan

CAREER OBJECTIVE

I am a detail-oriented individual with a doctoral program in Dairy Microbiology and 5 years of research experience in Fermented dairy products and Probiotics development. Additionally, I have 5 years of experience in clinical microbiology. I aim to contribute my expertise to advance scientific research and align with organizational objectives. My recognized intellect and strong work ethic ensure my commitment to making substantial contributions to your company's goals.

DoB: 20th June 1989

Address

H. No. 2440A, street No 3, Behind new bus stand, Chaman colony, Ghaziabad, Uttar Pradesh

Mobile: +919654058306

Email:

mohdrizwan510@gmail.com

LANGUAGES

Hindi, English, Urdu

HOBBIES

Bike Riding, Traveling, Trekking, Photography, Cooking, Badminton, Volleyball, Sketching etc.

EDUCATIONAL QUALIFICATIONS

Ph.D. Dairy Microbiology (2017-2024)

University: National Dairy Research Institute, Karnal

Research Title: "Development and assessment of α -glucosidase and DPP-IV inhibitory peptide-rich fermented camel milk with indigenous Lactobacillus cultures in a rat model."

❖ M.Sc. Microbiology (2010 − 2012)

University: Chaudhary Charan Singh University, Meerut.

B.Sc. Life Science (2006–2009)

University: Ch. Charan Singh University, Meerut.

College: M.M.H. College, Ghaziabad.

❖ Post Graduate Diploma in Food Safety and Quality Management (PGDFSQM) (2013-2014)

University: IGNOU, Delhi.

❖ Diploma on Technology of Fermented Cheese Ice-cream and By-

products (2020-2021)

University: IGNOU, Delhi.

❖ Diploma in Food Laws and Standards (2020-2021)

University: IGNOU, Delhi

❖ Three-month Certificate in Financial Accounting (CFA) (2007)

Dharmendra Institute of Computer Technology, Ghaziabad

WORK EXPERIENCE

- ❖ Working as a **Senior Research Fellow** at **ICAR-NDRI**, **Karnal** (2018 to till now)
- ❖ Worked as a **Teaching Assistant** at **ICAR-NDRI**, **Karnal** (2022-2023)
- ❖ Worked as **Digital Mitra** for 2 years under Food Safety Mitra Scheme of **FSSAI** and Eat Right India (2020-2022)
- ❖ Worked 7 months as **Microbiologist** in Asian institute of Medical Sciences, Faridabad. (2017)
- ❖ Worked 10 months as a **Microbiologist** in Premia Laboratories, Gurugram. (2016)
- ❖ Worked 17 moths as **Microbiologist** in Max Healthcare, New Delhi. (2014-16)
- ❖ Worked 11 months as **Scientific Officer-Microbiology** in Metropolis Healthcare Ltd, New Delhi (2013-14).
- ❖ Worked 8 months as **Technician-Microbiology** in Yashoda Hospital, Ghaziabad (2013).

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

- Microbiological Analysis and Laboratory Management: Over the course of 5 years, I have gained hands-on experience in microbiological analysis of pathogens within a NABL certified healthcare system. My role included managing laboratory operations, ensuring compliance with NABL standards, and overseeing equipment maintenance, supply procurement, and safety protocols.
- Research Expertise: During my Ph.D., I dedicated 5 years to research in dairy microbiology. My work focused on probiotic strain isolation and characterization, fermented dairy product development, peptide identification, and in-vitro and in-vivo analysis of its activity. This extensive research experience has honed my analytical skills and data analysis capabilities.
- Microbiological Techniques: Proficient in various microbiological techniques, including
 isolation and identification of bacteria and fungi, biochemical analysis, antimicrobial analysis,
 and more.
- Pathogen Handling: Demonstrated extensive experience in pathogen handling, ensuring adherence to rigorous safety protocols.
- **Fermentation Technology**: Possess expertise in fermentation technology, including hands-on experience with laboratory-scale fermenters.
- **High-End Equipment Proficiency:** Hands-on knowledge of working with high-end equipment such as HPLC, GC-MS, and AAS, showcasing a commitment to precision and accuracy in analytical processes.

- **Animal Handling:** Experienced in the ethical handling of small animals, specifically rats and mice, for research purposes.
- NABL Compliances: Sound knowledge and experience in adhering to NABL compliances, ensuring the highest standards of quality in laboratory practices.
- **Grant Proposals and Research Funding:** Successfully wrote research grant proposals and secured funding, including an ICMR-SRF grant, demonstrating a proactive approach to funding research initiatives.
- **Teaching Assistant:** Taught M. Tech students of Dairy Microbiology and Food safety for one semester as a Teaching Assistant.

PROJECTS

Ph.D. Research work under the supervision of Dr. Shilpa Vij, Principal Scientist, Dairy Microbiology Division, ICAR-NDRI, Karnal, on the topic entitled "Development and assessment of α-glucosidase and DPP-IV inhibitory peptide-rich fermented camel milk with indigenous Lactobacillus cultures in a rat model." Funded by ICAR-NDRI.

NATIONAL AWARDS/FELLOWSHIP

- **➤ UGC-NET 2022**
- > Indian Council of Medical Research Senior Research Fellow (ICMR-SRF)- 2022
- ➤ Indian Council of Agriculture Research- National Eligibility Test (ICAR-NET) Agriculture Microbiology- 2018
- ➤ Indian Council of Agriculture Research National Dairy Research Institute Ph.D. Fellowship- 2017
- ➤ GATE Life Science 2017

MEMBERSHIP

➤ Indian Dairy Association membership 2023-2024

PUBLICATIONS

Published a review article on the title, 'Mucormycosis defence strategies: Insights from cow
colostrum whey lactoferrin and peptides' in The Pharma Innovation Journal 2023; SP-12(11):
1795-1800 Authors Thakur N, Dhillon HS, Kaura R, Sain M, Rizwan M, Vij S.

\triangleright	Published a Hindi article on the title, "adda adda adda adda adda adda adda ad	_ <i>"</i>
	in "National dairy Mela Samarika-2023", Mohammad Rizwan, Nishchal Thakur and Shil	lpa
	Vij, Page no 107-108.	

- ➤ Published a Hindi article on the title, "□□□□□□□□□□□□□□□□□□□□□" in "National dairy Mela Samarika-2023", Dipti A. Waghmode, Mohammad Rizwan, and Shilpa Vij, Page no 7-10.
- ➤ Published a chapter on the title "Plant-derived natural bioactive compounds as potential therapies for corona viruses and other SARS-related infections: future perspectives", Ajeet Singh^{1,2}, Nalini Trivedi^{3*}, Prashant Goel⁴, Mohammad Rizwan⁴, Neha Patwa⁵, And Nikhil Mehta⁵.
- Published a chapter on the title "Antiviral activities of medicinal plants and bioactive compounds against human viral pathogens: update on preclinical and clinical trial", Ajeet Singh^{1,2*}, Nikhil Mehta³, Neha Patwa³, Shivani Kumari⁴, Poonam Bangia⁵, Prashant Goel⁶, Mohammad Rizwan⁶, And Navneet Bithel¹
- ➤ Editing and compilation of Training Compendium of 10-Days Hands-on Training on "Preparation of Functional Fermented Dairy Products", sponsored by the Govt. of India's SCSP (Scheduled Caste Sub Plan) Scheme at Dairy Microbiology Division, ICAR-NDRI, Karnal on 12-21st July 2023, Pages 136 Nos.
- ➤ Published Training Chapter on the title "Functional Fermented Dairy Foods: An overview", at page no 01-05, in training compendium of 10-Days Hands-on Training on "Preparation of Functional Fermented Dairy Products", sponsored by the Govt. of India's SCSP (Scheduled Caste Sub Plan) Scheme at Dairy Microbiology Division, ICAR-NDRI, Karnal on 12-21st July 2023.
- ➤ Published Training Chapter on the title "Preparation of Bio-functional yoghurt and sensory evaluation" at page no 84-90, in training compendium of 10-Days Hands-on Training on "Preparation of Functional Fermented Dairy Products", sponsored by the Govt. of India's SCSP (Scheduled Caste Sub Plan) Scheme at Dairy Microbiology Division, ICAR-NDRI, Karnal on 12-21st July 2023.
- ➤ Published Training Chapter on the title "Preparation of functional Dairy and whey beverages", at page no 113-119, in training compendium of 10-Days Hands-on Training on "Preparation of Functional Fermented Dairy and whey beverages", sponsored by the Govt. of India's SCSP (Scheduled Caste Sub Plan) Scheme at Dairy Microbiology Division, ICAR-NDRI, Karnal on 12-21st July 2023.

> Pamphlet and Awareness article Publication on the topic "Stubble Burning" in Hindi at Agriculture academy of Haryana in 2020.

AWARDS & ACHIEVEMENTS

- > Consolation prize winner of 3000/- as a Young Investigator for poster presentation on title "Development and assessment of α-glucosidase and DPP-IV inhibitory peptide-rich fermented camel milk with indigenous Lactobacillus cultures" in the 13th India Probiotics Symposium, "Science Based Evidence on the Benefits of Probiotics for Human Health" organised by the Gut Microbiota and Probiotic Science Foundation (India), on 25th & 26th March 2023.
- First Prize Winner for the product Raagi Amra-khand and Raagi Mango Lassi in the Milk millet based functional food category of the Innovative Millet Food Competition organised by the Dairy Technology Division of the ICAR-NDRI, Karnal on 4th March 2023.

Consolation Prize in Poster presentation in Hindi titled as "
at NDRI, on 22 nd Sept 2023.

- ➤ First prize for Gene □□□ Meme, organised by Microbiologists Society, India (Delhi Unit) in collaboration with Sookshma, held on 9th January 2022.
- > Third prize for poster presentation on topic "Isolation of Lactobacillus strain with α-glucosidase inhibitory and DPP-IV inhibitory activities from camel milk" in 27th International Conference of International Academy of physical sciences (CONIAPS XXVII) on "Advances in Food Science and Technology" 26th -28th Oct 2021.
- First Prize winner in **DuPont Nutri-Scholar Award-2020 (National level competition)** for making "**Nutri-Poi with Soymus**" in Quick Style Lunch Category for Academic year 220-2021, Conducted by Danisco, PlanIt and DuPont India.

EXTRA-CURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

- ➤ Training Co-ordinator for 10-Days Hands-on Training on "Preparation of Functional Fermented Dairy Products", sponsored by the Govt. of India's SCSP (Scheduled Caste Sub Plan) Scheme at Dairy Microbiology Division, ICAR-NDRI, Karnal on 12-21st July 2023.
- ➤ Co-ordinator of the Dairy Mela-2023 stall for Dairy Microbiology Division (ICAR-NDRI)
- ➤ Co-ordinator of the Dairy Mela-2020 stall for Dairy Microbiology Division (ICAR-NDRI).
- ➤ Participated as an **Organising Committee Member** in **NDRI Global Alumni Scientific Meet** held on 15-17th March 2019.
- ➤ Participated in the 'Debate Competition (General Cleanliness Awareness)' held during "Swachhata Pakhwada" on 29th Dec, 2018 under Swachh Bharat Abhiyan Organized by Dairy Microbiology Division, ICAR-NDRI.

SEMINARS AND CONFERENCE PARTICIPATIONS

- Poster presentation at 50th Dairy Industry Conference on "Development of antidiabetic bioactive peptides through the production purification process in camel milk, utilizing an indigenous proteolytic lactobacillus strain" organised by Indian Dairy Association (South zone) and IDA Telangana chapter during 04-06 March, 2024 at HITEX Exhibition Center, Izzat Nagar, Hyderabad.
- ➤ Participation in the 10th National Seminar on "Indian Dairy & Food Industry in the Amrit Kaal: Opportunities and Challenges" organised by NDRI Graduate Association & ICAR-National Dairy Research Institute, Karnal, Held on 29-30th Sept 2023.
- ➤ Poster Presentation at NGASM for innovative Idea competition, titled as "Waste to fuel: Ethanol production for its application as boiler fuel" at NDRI, 2023.
- ➤ Poster Presentation at 10th National Seminar on "Indian Dairy & Food Industry in the Amrit Kaal: Opportunities and Challenges" organised by NDRI Graduate Association, titled as "Development of Fermented Camel Milk with Anti-diabetic Properties" at NDRI, Held on 29-30th Sept 2023.
- ➤ Poster presentation on topic "LC-MS Identification of Antimicrobial Bioactive Peptides Derived from Camel Milk by Microbial Fermentation" in 11th Annual Meeting of Proteomics Society, India, 2019 and International Conference on Proteomics for System Integrated Bio-Omics, One Health, and Food Safety 2nd 4th Dec 2019.

WORKSHOPS

- ➤ One day workshop on "CME on Good Laboratory Practice (GLP)" under IDP-NAHEP held on 09th Aug 2023 at ICAR-NDRI, Karnal.
- National Workshop on "**Drafting of Patent Application & Patent Filling Procedure**" held on 26th Aug 2022, at ICAR-NDRI, Karnal.
- ➤ International Web-Workshop on "Innovative and Emerging Technologies for Food Safety & Nutritional Quality" held on 12th May, 13th May and 25th May 2021, at ICAR-NDRI, Karnal.
- ➤ Online Worshop on "Molecular Dynamics Simulations and In-Silico Drug Designing" conducted by CytoGene, held on 12-13th June 2021.
- ➤ Workshop on "Genome Editing in Farm Animals for Improved Productivity and Health" held on 3rd March 2020 at ICAR-NDRI, Karnal.
- ➤ Workshop on "Advances in Starter Culture Technology" held on 14th Jan 2020 at ICAR-NDRI, Karnal, and Sponsored by IDP-NAHEP.
- Workshop on "Mammalian Genome Editing by CRISPR Technique" held on 14th Jan 2020 at ICAR-NDRI, Karnal, and Sponsored by IDP-NAHEP.
- ➤ Workshop on "Advances in Starter Culture Technology" held on 12th Dec, 2019 at ICAR-NDRI, Karnal, and Sponsored by IDP-NAHEP.

TRAININGS

- ➤ Workshop cum Training on Basic Food Microbiology and Microbial Diseases by the collaboration of ICAR-NDRI and Purdue University, and Sponsored by IDP-NAHEP (1010209), during 4-15th Sept 2023 at ICAR-NDRI, Karnal.
- ➤ Operation and Software application training for Vitek 2 Compact by Biomerieux at Metropolis Healthcare Ltd, New Delhi, in 2014.
- > Operation and maintenance of Urine Analyzer, of Laura M, by Transasia at Metropolis Healthcare Ltd, New Delhi, in 2014.

WEBINARS

- National Webinar on "Recent Advances in Dairy Process Engineering" held on 24th to 28th Aug 2020, organised by Dept of Food Process Engineering, College of Food and Dairy Technology, Kodivalli in association of Food Scientists & Technologists (India), Chennai Chapter.
- ➤ Webinar on "Why IPR?" on Intellectual Property Rights organised by S.B. Jain Institute of Technology, Management & Research, Nagpur held on 26th June, 2020.
- Webinar on "Importance of Rheology in the Development of Nano-packaging Materials" on 28th Aug 2020, organised by Department of Food Engineering, NIFTEM.
- ➤ International Webinar on "Process-driven Organic Contaminants in Food and Mitigation Strategies" on 10th Sept 2020, organised by Department of Agriculture and Environmental Sciences, NIFTEM.
- National Webinar on "Licensing System in Dairy and Food Industry" held on 3rd Oct, 2020, organised by College of Dairy Science & Food Technology, Raipur.
- National Webinar on "Trends in Detection of Adulterants in Milk and Ghee" held on 15th Sept 2021, organised by Dairy Chemistry Department SMC College of Dairy Science, Kamdhenu University, Anand, Gujrat.
- ➤ Webinar on "Aflatoxin & Antibiotic Residues in Milk" held on 15th May, 2021, organised by Indian Dairy Association, Tamil Nadu Chapter.
- ➤ International Webinar on "Impact of Climate Change and Heat Stress on Dairy Cattle and Mitigation Strategies" held on 20th June, 2020, organised by Animal Physiology Division of ICAR-NDRI, Karnal.
- National Webinar on "Pharmacological Potential of A1 and A2 Milk: Myths and Facts" held on 11th July 2020, by ISVPT.
- ➤ Online National Conference on "Implementing Strategies to Achieve Food Security and Food Sustainable Partnership: Progress and Challenges" conducted on 29 30th July 2021, organised by College of Food and Dairy Technology, Koduvelli, Chennai.

SKILLS

TECHNICAL SKILLS	SOFT SKILLS	INSTRUMENT	
➤ MS office utilities	EffectiveCommunication	> HPLC	

➤ General internet tools > Leadership ➤ Ultrafiltration

> Self-motivating > PCR ➤ Adobe Photoshop

> ZOOM > Positive attitude > Spectrophotometer

➤ Microsoft Team > GCMS

REFERENCES

Dr. Anil Kumar Puniya Dr. D. C. Sharma Dr. Shilpa Vij

Principal Scientist Principal Scientist **Assistant Professor**

Dairy Microbiology Division Dairy Microbiology Division Shakuntala Misra National **ICAR-NDRI**

Rehabilitation University, Lucknow Karnal-132001, Haryana, Karnal-132001, Haryana,

Mob: 09456262770

Tel: +919996262863 Mob: 8395913535 Email: dcsharma@dsmnru.ac.in

Email: shilpavij.n@gmail.com Email: akpuniya@gmail.com

Declaration

ICAR-NDRI

I hereby declare that the above-mentioned information is true to the best of my knowledge and belief.

Place: Date: (Signature)